A Guide to the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) records FA084
Rockefeller Archive Center
International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) records
1945-1977
Rockefeller Archive Center
International Basic Economy Corporation
Rockefeller, Rodman (1932-2000)
FA084
157.46 Cubic Feet
This collection consists of: 107 record cartons, 52 document boxes, 1 flat box, 250 reels of microfilm, 2550 sheets of microfiche, photographs, and audio tapes.
Arrangement note
The IBEC records are arranged in 14 series:
Series 1 - Miscellaneous
Series 2 - Projects and Proposals
Series 3 - Public Relations and Publicity
Series 4 - Services and Consultants
Series 5 - General Information - Data and Research
Series 6 - Conferences
Series 7 - Associations
Series 8 - IBEC
Series 9 - IBEC History Project Files
Series 10 - Rodman C. Rockefeller Files
Series 11 - Photographs
Series IBEC - Microforms
Series J - Microforms
Series R - Microfilm
Biographical/Historical note
The International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC) (1947-1977) was founded by Nelson A. Rockefeller in January 1947. The Corporation was developed as a private business enterprise that would focus on upgrading the "basic economies" of lesser-developed nations by lowering food prices, building sound housing, mobilizing savings, and fostering industrialization. The objective was for the business to be profitable and sustainable, and to encourage others, especially nationals, to establish competitive businesses and thereby establish a "multiplier" development effect. In it's early years, 1947-1955, IBEC was especially focused in Latin America, specifically Brazil and Venezuela. The subsidiary Venezuelan Basic Economy Corporation (VBEC) was formed, which was divided into several companies: a fishing company, a food wholesaling company, which later became a retail supermarket company, and a milk company.
In Brazil, IBEC divided into five companies which provided specialized services to farmers. These companies individually focused in the areas of: hybrid seeds, hog experimentation, grain storage, helicopter crop-dusting, and mechanized agricultural services. IBEC also invested modestly in Brazilian manufacturing and investment banking.
During the period 1956-1971, IBEC's mission broadened to encompass new activities, such as mutual funds, housing, poultry, and soluble coffee companies. During this time IBEC expanded into other geographical areas, eventually having operations in thirty-three countries on four continents.
By 1972, the subsidiaries and joint ventures were reorganized into five operating groups: food, housing, distribution, industrial and financial services. The food group aimed at increasing the quality and yield of basic edible commodities in various host nations. The housing group concentrated on predominantly prefabricated low to medium-priced housing in the United States, Mexico, Peru, Puerto Rico and Brazil. The distribution group operated cash and carry supermarkets in several Latin American countries. The industrial group, including three U.S. subsidiaries, produced equipment for American industrial markets. The financial services group was instrumental in the development of indigenous capital markets in Brazil, Spain and Thailand.
In 1973, the company began a divestment program and by 1980, when IBEC merged with Booker McConnell Limited, was primarily engaged in agriculturally-related endeavors. In 1985 the company name was changed from IBEC, Inc. to Arbor Acres Farm, Inc.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Appraisal
It is believed that the original records filmed to microforms were destroyed following the filming. It is therefore likely that there is little to no overlap in content between paper records and microforms other than material which may have been maintained in more than one file location during active use of the documents.
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, publications, minutes, dockets, photographs, tape recordings, and films. The collection was created by the IBEC files department, and many documents contain department seals and marginal notes in pencil.
Subjects include agriculture in Latin America; the economics of agriculture; foreign business enterprise; economic development in Latin America; the food industry in Latin America, including egg production, fisheries, food crops, food distribution, and food production; housing; hybrid corn and hybrid seeds; investment banking and investment trusts; dried milk; poultry breeding; food preservation; coffee processing; swine breeding; silk manufacture and trade; and shopping centers and supermarkets in Latin America.
Among the companies represented in these files are: Arbor Acres Farm, Inc., Booker McConnell Limited, Cinva-Ram, and Venezuelan Basic Economy Corporation (VBEC).
Among the individuals who appear in the files are: Victor Andrade, Romulo Betancourt, David Dubinsky, John B. Griffing, Francis A. Jamieson, K. J. Kadow, Donald E. Meads, Robert Moses, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Rodman C. Rockefeller, and Winthrop Rockefeller.
Among the countries represented in this collection are: the Argentine Republic, Brazil, Bolivia, Chile, Colombia, Cuba, Ecuador, Latin America, Iran, Italy, Mexico, Peru, Puerto Rico, South America, Spain, Thailand, and Venezuela.
Related Archival Materials note
For related materials at RAC see:
FA079 American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) records
FA339 Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, AIA-IBEC, Series B
FA768 Wayne G. Broehl papers
Researchers may also wish to consult Wayne G. Broehl's book, "The International Basic Economy Corporation," which is available in the Rockefeller Archive Center Library.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Rodman C. Rockefeller donated the IBEC records to the Rockefeller Archive Center in 1985.
Business; Housing; Food production and natural resources; Food production and natural resources -- Latin America; Business enterprises, Foreign; Agriculture; Latin America; Agriculture -- Latin America; Economics; Economic development; Economic development -- Latin America; Hunger; Commerce; Commerce -- Latin America
- Miscellaneous, 1955-1977; 1; 6.46 Cubic Feet 17 letter document boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes information about companies, institutions and government representatives, and their relation with IBEC. Most of the collection is in English, but some records are Spanish, Italian, Portuguese, French and German.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - A - Ag, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Correspondence, annual report, brochure, report, circular, booklet, catalogue. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Ai - Anderson, 1964-1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Correspondence, memorandum, report, newsletter, journal, news clipping, prospectus, annual report, telegram, telex. Documents in this folder are in English, Spanish and Portuguese.
  - Adela Investment Company S. A., 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence, journal, report, brochure, press release, bulletin, news clipping, telegram, annual report, telex. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Ant - Ayres, 1963-1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Correspondence, annual report, brochure, magazine, report, journal, newsletter. Documents in this folder are in English, Spanish and French.
  - The Atlantic Institute, 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Correspondence, book, article. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - B, 1962-1975 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Correspondence, report, prospectus, brochure, journal, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Br, 1961-1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, journal. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Bu, 1961-1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Correspondence, report, brochure. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - C - Ce, 1960-1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Correspondence, news clipping, report, memorandum, journal, prospectus, brochure, annual report. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Ch - Cl, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, memorandum, annual report, balance. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Co - Cz, 1960-1976 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, memorandum, annual report, journal. Documents in this folder are in English and French.
  - D - Di, 1965-1977 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Correspondence, brochure, news clipping, report, memorandum, telegram, article, telex, book. Documents in this folder are in English, Portuguese and Spanish.
  - Deltec Panamerica S. A., 1959-1975 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum, annual report, news clipping, journal. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Do - Du, 1962-1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum, annual report, news clipping, brochure, balance, contract. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - E - Ex, 1964-1976 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Correspondence, brochure, report, memorandum, prospectus, telegram, booklet, journal. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Export Procurement Corporation, 1960-1972 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Correspondence, report, news clipping, brochure, balance, memorandum, bulletin. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - F - Fo, 1968-1974 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    Correspondence, report, news clipping, telegram, prospectus, brochure, annual report. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Ford Foundation, 1968-1975 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    Correspondence, journal, report, memorandum, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Fr - Fu, 1963-1976 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    Correspondence, brochure, newsletter, report, news clipping, telegram, annual report, telex. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - G - Gi, 1964-1976 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    Correspondence, report, news clipping, annual report, journal, telegram, telex. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - General Mills, Inc., 1967-1974 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    Correspondence, memorandum, brochure, report, bulletin, annual report, magazine, press release, news clipping, telegram. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Gl - Gu, 1961-1976 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    Correspondence, report, news clipping, speech, brochure, memorandum, annual report, magazine, book, photograph, press release. Documents in this folder are in English, Spanish and Portuguese.
  - Gordon Johnson International, Inc., 1962-1964 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    Correspondence, brochure, journal, report. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Harvard University, 1967-1975 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    Journal, bulletin, brochure, report. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Harvard University, 1961-1975 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    Correspondence, memorandum, article, report, program, application. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - H - Ho, 1959-1976 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum, brochure, journal. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Hu - Hy, 1970-1975 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    Correspondence, report, prospectus, brochure, newsletter, article. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Im - International Development Services, Inc., 1960-1977 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    Correspondence, memorandum, report, brochure, annual report, bulletin. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Industrial Raw Materials Corporation, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 29)
    Correspondence, memorandum, report. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Inter-American Investment Development Center, 1966-1969 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    Correspondence, memorandum, report, brochure, journal, program. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - International Arts & Sciences Press (IASP), 1966-1967 (Box 10, Folder 31)
    Correspondence, journal. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - International Business Machine Corporation (IBM), 1964-1970 (Box 10, Folder 32)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, annual report, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - International Executive Service Corps - It, 1965-1975 (Box 10, Folder 33)
    Correspondence, memorandum, report, journal, annual report, brochure, newsletter. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Investors Diversified Services, 1961-1969 (Box 10, Folder 34)
    Correspondence, report, news bureau, annual report, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - J, 1967-1974 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    Correspondence, report, telegram, telex, brochure, memorandum, bulletin, journal, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English, German and French.
  - K, 1961-1974 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, journal, news clipping, telegram, telex, press release. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - L, 1964-1975 (Box 11, Folder 37)
    Correspondence, telegram, telex, memorandum, report, balance, annual report, news clipping, brochure. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - M - Michigan, 1963-1975 (Box 11, Folder 38)
    Correspondence, memorandum, telegram, prospectus, news clipping, report, journal. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Middle East, 1955-1973 (Box 12, Folder 39)
    Correspondence, telegram, telex, report, memorandum, speech, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Mitsui & Co., Inc., 1964-1976 (Box 12, Folder 40)
    Correspondence, memorandum, brochure, journal, report, news clipping, telegram, telex. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Na - Nu, 1966-1975 (Box 12, Folder 41)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, program, annual report, journal, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Nebraska Consolidated Mills Company, 1962-1969 (Box 12, Folder 42)
    Correspondence, report, annual report. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Ob - Ov, 1969-1976 (Box 13, Folder 43)
    Correspondence, report, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Pa - Po, 1964-1976 (Box 13, Folder 44)
    Correspondence, report, telegram, memorandum, annual report, journal, brochure, prospectus. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - J. C. Penney Company, Inc., 1967-1973 (Box 13, Folder 45)
    Correspondence, memorandum, journal. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Pr - Pu, 1967-1973 (Box 13, Folder 46)
  - Politics, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 47)
    Correspondence, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Power Industry, 1962-1972 (Box 13, Folder 48)
    Correspondence, newspaper, report, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Q, 1963-1971 (Box 13, Folder 49)
    Correspondence, newsletter, memorandum, news clipping, telegram, photograph, journal. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - R, 1966-1975 (Box 13, Folder 50)
    Correspondence, report, news clipping, memorandum, brochure. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - Ralston Purina Company, 1959-1972 (Box 14, Folder 51)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, memorandum, news clipping, minutes, telegram, magazine, draft. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - S - Sayan, 1963-1973 (Box 14, Folder 52)
    Correspondence, report, telegram, memorandum, notes. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Schafer Brothers, Ltd., 1958-1974 (Box 14, Folder 53)
    Correspondence, report, telegram, telex, annual report, news clippings, memorandum, catalogue. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Sch - Sim, 1961-1975 (Box 15, Folder 54)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum, news clipping, annual report, brochure, telex, magazine. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Si - Sp, 1968-1975 (Box 15, Folder 55)
  - The Singer Company, New York, 1965-1971 (Box 15, Folder 56)
    Correspondence, memorandum, news clipping, annual report, article. Documents in this folder are in English and Italian.
  - The Singer Company, 1958-1969 (Box 15, Folder 57)
    Correspondence, journal, lecture, report, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English, Italian and Portuguese.
  - St - Sz, 1968-1974 (Box 16, Folder 58)
    Correspondence, report, journal, prospectus, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - T, 1968-1975 (Box 16, Folder 59)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, annual report, book, telex. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - U, 1968-1976 (Box 16, Folder 60)
    Correspondence, memorandum, report, telex, booklet, magazine, quarterly. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - V, 1967-1975 (Box 16, Folder 61)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, news clippings, newsletter. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - W, 1960-1976 (Box 17, Folder 62)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, journal, annual report, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - X - Z, 1963-1972 (Box 17, Folder 63)
    Correspondence, report, brochure, annual report, telegram, journal. Documents in this folder are in English.
- Projects and Proposals, 1932-1977; 2; 19.37 Cubic Feet 51 letter document boxes
  The records in this series include information about projects and proposals that IBEC received from companies and government representatives from all over the world. There is some correspondence with important politicians in Latin America, such as the President of Chile, Eduardo Frei.
  There are some lists of persons from IBEC who used the records. There are a lot of margin notes in pencil from the IBEC files department that describe the importance of the document; for example, in the folder titled "Japan-Industrialization", there is a label that says "for limited use only" with names of the people in IBEC who can read this information. Other marginal notes comment on facts about the operations, such as "this project did not materialize."
  Most of the records are in English, but there are several documents in other languages, such as Portuguese, Spanish, French, Italian, German, Danish, and Greek, some with English translations.
  This series is arranged alphabetically, first by country, continent, or region, and thereunder by industry.
  - Projects & Proposals - General, 1962-1967 (Box 17, Folder 64)
    Correspondence, memorandum, report, telegram. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Africa - Agriculture, 1965-1966 (Box 17, Folder 65)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Africa - Coffee, 1958-1967 (Box 17, Folder 66)
    Correspondence, telegram, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Africa - Marketing - Supermarkets, 1956-1971 (Box 17, Folder 67)
    Correspondence, news clipping, report, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - Africa - Mining, 1948-1972 (Box 18, Folder 68)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum, brochure. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Africa - Development, 1947-1976 (Box 18, Folder 69)
    Correspondence, annual report, report, prospectus, brochure, photograph, journal, memorandum, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English, French and Portuguese.
  - Projects - General, 1947-1948 (Box 18, Folder 70)
    Report, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Africa - Poultry, 1971-1972 (Box 18, Folder 71)
    Correspondence, report. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Africa - Sugar, 1958-1961 (Box 18, Folder 72)
  - Africa - Transportation, 1949 (Box 18, Folder 73)
  - Alaska - Development, 1969-1974 (Box 18, Folder 74)
  - Argentina - Banking, 1960 (Box 18, Folder 75)
    Correspondence, memorandum, cablegram. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - Argentina - Development, 1962-1972 (Box 18, Folder 76)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Argentina - Development - Gas, 1963-1967 (Box 19, Folder 77)
    Correspondence, bulletin, memorandum, brochure, telegram, telex, report, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Argentina - Financing, 1959-1970 (Box 19, Folder 78)
    Correspondence, memorandum, telegram, report. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Argentina - Fishing Industry, 1957-1971 (Box 19, Folder 79)
    Correspondence, report, telegram, magazine, memorandum, news leaflet. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Argentina - Food Processing, 1961-1972 (Box 19, Folder 80)
    Correspondence, brochure, report. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Argentina - Housing, 1955-1971 (Box 19, Folder 81)
    Correspondence, draft, memorandum, balance, report. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Argentina - Manufacturing, 1960-1964 (Box 19, Folder 82)
  - Argentina - Mining, 1959-1969 (Box 20, Folder 83)
    Correspondence. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Argentina - Poultry Processing, 1960-1962 (Box 20, Folder 84)
  - Argentina - Shopping Centers, 1968-1969 (Box 20, Folder 85)
  - Argentina - Slaughterhouses, 1966-1970 (Box 20, Folder 86)
    Correspondence, balance, memorandum, prospectus, telex. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Argentina - Wineries, 1964-1973 (Box 20, Folder 87)
    Correspondence, telex, memorandum, balance, report. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Australia - Development, 1961-1975 (Box 20, Folder 88)
    Correspondence, report, memorandum, news clipping, telegram, brochure. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Australia - Mutual Investment Funds, 1968 (Box 20, Folder 89)
  - Australia - Marketing - Shopping Centers, 1954-1957 (Box 20, Folder 90)
  - Australia - Poultry, 1962-1975 (Box 20, Folder 91)
  - Austria - Development, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 92)
  - Bangladesh - Development, 1973 (Box 20, Folder 93)
  - Belgium - Development, 1970 (Box 20, Folder 94)
    Correspondence, brochure. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Bolivia - Development, 1947-1970 (Box 20, Folder 95)
    Correspondence, news clipping, report, memorandum. Documents in this folder are in English and Spanish.
  - Bolivia - Housing, 1961-1969 (Box 20, Folder 96)
  - Bolivia - Marketing - Supermarkets, 1966-1970 (Box 20, Folder 97)
    Correspondence, telex. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Brazil - Agribusiness, 1970-1976 (Box 20, Folder 98)
    Correspondence, memorandum, speech, balance, report. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - Brazil - Agriculture, 1947-1974 (Box 20, Folder 99)
    Correspondence, memorandum, news clipping. Documents in this folder are in English, Portuguese and French.
  - Brazil - Assembly Plants, 1966-1971 (Box 21, Folder 100)
    Correspondence, balance, telegram, cablegram, brochure, report, telex. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - Brazil - Investment Banking, 1967-1972 (Box 21, Folder 101)
    Correspondence, report, telegram. Documents in this folder are in English.
  - Brazil - Coffee - Soluble, 1966-1972 (Box 21, Folder 102)
    Correspondence, news clipping, memorandum, draft. Also correspondence on microfilm. Documents in this folder are in English and Portuguese.
  - Brazil - Coffee - Soluble, 1953-1967 (Box 21, Folder 103)